I'd like for you to take a moment to imagine this with me.
أود منك أن تأخذ لحظة أن تتصور هذا معي.
You're a little girl of five years old.
أنتِ فتاة صغيرة في الخامسة من عمرك.
Sitting in front of a mirror,
جالسة أمام المرآة،
you ask yourself,
تسألين نفسك،
"Do I exist?"
"هل أنا موجودة؟"
In this space, there is very little context,
في هذه المساحة، هنالك سياق ضئيل جداً،
and so you move into a different one,
ولذلك يمكنك الإنتقال إلى سياق مختلف،
one filled with people.
واحد مليئ بالناس.
Surely, now you know you're not a figment of your own imagination.
بالتأكيد، الآن أنتِ تعلمين أنكِ لست صورة من نسج خيالك.
You breathe their air.
أنت تتنفسين هواءهم.
You see them,
أنت ترينهم،
so they must see you.
لذلك هم يجب أن يروك.
And yet, you still can't help but wonder:
ومع ذلك، لا يمكنك سوى أن تتسألين:
Do I only exist when people speak to me?
هل أنا موجودة فقط عندما يتحدث الناس معي؟
Pretty heavy thoughts for a child, right?
أفكار ثقيلة جدا لطفلة، أليس كذلك؟
But through various artworks that reflect upon our society,
ولكن من خلال مختلف الأعمال الفنية التي تنعكس علي مجتمعنا،
I came to understand how a young black girl can grow up
جئت لأفهم كيف يمكن لفتاة سوداء أن تكبر
feeling as if she's not seen, and perhaps she doesn't exist.
مع شعور انها لاتري، وربما أنها غير موجودة.
You see, if young people don't have positive images of themselves
كما ترى، إذا كان الشباب ليس لديهم صور إيجابية عن أنفسهم
and all that remains are negative stereotypes,
وكل ما تبقى لهم هي القوالب النمطية السلبية،
this affects their self-image.
هذا يؤثر على صورة الذات لهم.
But it also affects the way that the rest of society treats them.
ولكنه يؤثر أيضا على الطريقة التي يعاملهم بها بقية المجتمع .
I discovered this
لقد إكتشفت الاتي
having lived in Cape Town for about five years at the time.
بعد أن عشت في كيب تاون لمدة خمس سنوات في ذلك الوقت.
I felt a deep sense of dislocation and invisibility.
شعرت بإحساس عميق من التفكك والإخفتاء.
I couldn't see myself represented.
لم أتمكن من رؤية نفسي حاضرة.
I couldn't see the women who've raised me,
لم أتمكن من رؤية النساء اللواتي ربينني،
the ones who've influenced me,
أولئك اللاتي أثرن علي،
and the ones that have made South Africa what it is today.
واللاتي صنعن جنوب أفريقيا كما هي عليه اليوم.
I decided to do something about it.
قررت أن افعل شيء ما حيال ذلك.
What do you think when you see this?
ماذا ستفكر عندما ترى هذا؟
If you were a black girl,
إذا كنت فتاة سوداء،
how would it make you feel?
كيف يمكن أن يجعلك هذا تشعر؟
Walking down the street,
تمشي في الشارع،
what does the city you live in say to you?
ماذا تقول لك المدينة التي تعيشين فيها؟
What symbols are present?
ما هي الرموز الموجودة؟
Which histories are celebrated?
ماهي التواريخ التي يحتفل بها؟
And on the other hand,
ومن ناحية أخرى،
which ones are omitted?
أي منها يتم تجاهله؟
You see, public spaces are hardly ever as neutral as they may seem.
كما ترى، الأماكن العامة تكون بالكاد محايدة كما قد تبدو.
I discovered this when I made this performance in 2013 on Heritage Day.
اكتشفت هذا عندما قمت بهذا الأداء في عام 2013 في يوم التراث.
Cape Town is teeming with masculine architecture,
كيب تاون مزدحمة بالعمارة الذكورية
monuments and statues,
الآثار والتماثيل،
such as Louis Botha in that photograph.
مثل لويس بوثا في تلك الصورة.
This overt presence of white colonial and Afrikaner nationalist men
هذا الوجود الطاغي للإستعماري الأبيض والرجال الأفارقة الوطنيين
not only echoes a social, gender and racial divide,
ليس فقط يردد أصداء إنقسامات إجتماعية، و جنسية وعنصرية،
but it also continues to affect the way that women --
ولكن أيضا يستمر في التأثير على الطريقة التي فيها النساء
and the way, particularly, black women --
و بالأخص، النساء السود
see themselves in relation to dominant male figures
ينظرن فيها لأنفسهن في علاقة مع تماثيل الذكور السائدة
in public spaces.
في الأماكن العامة.
For this reason, among others,
ولهذا السبب، وأسباب اخرى،
I don't believe that we need statues.
لا أعتقد أننا بحاجة إلى تماثيل.
The preservation of history and the act of remembering
الحفاظ على التاريخ وفعل التذكير
can be achieved in more memorable and effective ways.
يمكن أن يتحقق بطرق لا تنسى وأكثرفعالية.
As part of a year-long public holiday series,
كجزء من سلسلة عطلات عامة في سنة واحدة،
I use performance art as a form of social commentary
استخدمت الأداء الفني كشكل من أشكال التعليق الأجتماعي
to draw people's attention to certain issues,
للفت انتباه الناس إلى بعض القضايا،
as well as addressing the absence of the black female body
كما أعالج غياب تماثيل الإناث السود
in memorialized public spaces,
في الأماكن التذكارية العامة ،
especially on public holidays.
خاصة في العطلات الرسمية.
Women's Day was coming up.
كان يوم المرأة يقترب.
I looked at what the day means --
نظرت إلى ما يعنيه اليوم --
the Women's March to the union buildings in 1956,
مسيرة المرأة إلى مباني النقابة في عام 1956،
petitioning against the pass laws.
رفع عريضة ضد قوانين العبور.
Juxtaposed with the hypocrisy of how women are treated,
بجانب النفاق في كيفية معاملة النساء،
especially in public spaces today,
وخاصة في المساحت العامة اليوم،
I decided to do something about it.
قررت أن أفعل شيء ما حيال ذلك.
Headline:
العنوان:
[Women in miniskirt attacked at taxi rank]
[نساء في تنورات قصيرة هوجِمن في موقف التاكسي]
How do I comment on such polar opposites?
كيف يمكنني التعليق على هذه الأضداد؟
In the guise of my great-grandmother,
وفي زي جدتي العظيمة،
I performed bare-breasted,
لقد أديت عارية الصدر،
close to the taxi rank in KwaLanga.
بالقرب من موقف سيارات الأجرة في كوالانغا،
This space is also called Freedom Square,
وتسمى هذه الساحة أيضا ساحة الحرية،
where women were a part of demonstrations against apartheid laws.
حيث كانت النساء جزء من المظاهرات ضد قوانين الفصل العنصري.
I was not comfortable with women being seen as only victims in society.
لم أكن مرتاحة مع أن النساء يعتبرن الضحية الوحيدة في المجتمع.
You might wonder how people reacted to this.
قد تتساءل كيف تقاعل الناس على هذا.
(Video) Woman: (Cheering)
(فيديو) امرأة: (تهتف)
Woman 2 (offscreen): Yes!
امرأة 2 (خارج الشاشة): نعم!
Sethembile Msezane: Pretty cool, huh?
سيثمبيل مززان: رائع جدا، هه؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I realized that through my performances,
لذلك أدركت أنه من خلال أدائي،
I've been able to make regular people reflect upon their society,
قد كنت قادرة على جعل الناس العاديين، يفكرون في مجتمعهم،
looking at the past as well as the current democracy.
بنظروا للماضي وايضاً للديمقراطية الحالية.
(Video) Man (offscreen): She's been there since three o'clock.
(فيديو) رجل ( خارج الشاشة): لقد كانت هناك منذ الساعة الثالثة.
Man 2 (offscreen): Just before three. About an hour still?
رجل 2 (خارج الشاشة): قبل الثالثة. ولا تزال من حوالي ساعة؟
Man 1: Yeah. It's just a really hot day.
رجل 1: نعم. انه يوم ساخن حقاً.
Man 1: It's very interesting.
رجل 1: إنه مثير جدا للإهتمام.
It's very powerful.
قوي جدا.
I think it's cool.
أعتقد أنه رائع.
I think a lot of people are quick to join a group
أعتقد أن الكثير من الناس ستنضم سريعا للمجموعة
that's a movement towards something,
هذه حركة نحو شيء ما،
but not many people are ready to do something as an individual.
ولكن ليس الكثير من الناس على استعداد أن تفعل شيئا بشكل منفرد.
Man 2: So it's the individual versus the collective.
رجل 2: لذلك هو الفرد مقابل الجماعة.
Man 1: Yeah.
رجل 1: نعم.
So I think her pushing her own individual message in performance ...
لذلك أعتقد أنها تدفع برسالتها الفردية في الأداء ...
it's powerful.
إنه قوي.
Yeah, I think it's quite powerful that she's doing it on her own.
نعم، أعتقد أنه قوي جدا أن تفعل ذلك من تلقاء نفسها.
I'd be interested to know why she's using hair extensions as wings,
سأكون مهتما بمعرفة السبب لماذا تستخدم خصلات الشعر كأجنحة،
or whatever those things are meant to be.
أو أيا كان يقترض بتلك الأشياء أن تكون.
They are wings, yes?
هي أجنحة، نعم؟
Woman 3: With her standing there right now,
المرأة 3: مع وقوفها هناك الآن،
I think it's just my interpretation
أعتقد، وهذا فقط تفسيري الخاص
that we are bringing the statue down
أننا نحضر التمثال إلى أسفل
and bringing up something
ونجلب شيء ما
that's supposed to represent African pride, I think.
من المفترض أن يمثل الفخر الأفريقي، أعتقد.
Or something like that.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
Something should stand while Rhodes falls,
شيء يجب أن يقف في حين يسقط رودس،
I think that's what it's saying. Yeah.
أعتقد أن هذا ما تقوله. بلى.
Yes. Thank you.
نعم فعلا. شكرا.
Man 3: What is behind me represents the African culture.
رجل 3: ما هو خلفي يمثل الثقافة الأفريقية
We can't have the colonialist law,
لا يمكن أن يكون لدينا القانون الإستعماري،
so we need to remove all these colonial statues.
لذلك نحن بحاجة إلى إزالة كل هذه التماثيل الإستعمارية
We have have our own statues now,
لدينا التماثيل الخاصة بنا الآن،
our African leaders -- Bhambatha, Moshoeshoe, Kwame Nkrumah --
زعماءنا الأفارقة -- بهامباثا، موشوشو، كوامي نكروما --
all those who paid their lives for our liberation.
كل أولئك الذين دفعوا حياتهم لتحريرنا.
We can't continue in the 21st century,
لا يمكننا الإستمرار في القرن الحادي والعشرين
and after 21 years of democracy,
وبعد 21 عاما من الديمقراطية،
have the colonizers in our own country.
أن يكون لدينا مستعمرون في بلدنا.
They belong somewhere. Maybe in a museum; not here.
إنهم ينتمون الى مكان ما. ربما في متحف؛ ليس هنا.
I mean learning institutions, places where young people,
أعني مؤسسات التعليم، الأماكن حيث يتواجد الشباب،
young minds are being shaped.
يتم تشكيل عقول الشباب.
So we cannot continue to have Louis Botha, Rhodes, all these people,
لذلك لا يمكننا الاستمرار في الإحتفاظ بلويس بوثا، رودس، وكل هؤلاء الناس،
because they're representing the colonialism.
لأنهم يمثلون الاستعمار.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Sethembile Msezane: On April 9, 2015,
سيثمبيل مززان: في 9 أبريل 2015،
the Cecil John Rhodes statue was scheduled to be removed
تمثال سيسيل جون رودس كان من المقرر إزالته
after a month of debates for and against its removal
بعد شهر من المناقشات مع وضد إزالته
by various stakeholders.
من قبل مختلف أصحاب المصالح
This caused a widespread interest in statues in South Africa.
وقد تسبب ذلك في إهتمام واسع النطاق في التماثيل في جنوب أفريقيا.
Opinions varied, but the media focused on problematizing
وتفاوتت الآراء، ولكن وسائل الإعلام تركز على إشكالية
the removal of statues.
إزالة التماثيل.
On that -- well, that year, I had just begun my master's
على ذلك - حسنا، في ذلك العام، كنت قد بدأت للتو الماجستير
at the University of Cape Town.
في جامعة كيب تاون.
During the time of the debate of the statue,
في زمن الجدال حول التمثال،
I had been having reoccurring dreams
كنت احلم أحلاماً مكررة
about a bird.
عن طائر.
And so I started conjuring her
وهكذا بدأت إستحضاره
mentally, spiritually and through dress.
عقليا، روحيا ومن خلال اللباس.
On that day,
في ذلك اليوم،
I happened to be having a meeting with my supervisors,
حدث أن كان لي إجتماع مع المشرفين،
and they told me that the statue was going to fall on that day.
وقد اخبروني أن التمثال سوف يسقط في ذلك اليوم.
I told them that I'd explain later,
قلت لهم أنني سأشرح لاحقا،
but we had to postpone the meeting
ولكن كان علينا تأجيل الاجتماع
because I was going to perform her as the statue came down.
لأنني كنت ذاهبة لأدائها حين سقوط التمثال .
Her name was Chapungu.
كان إسمها تشابونغو.
She was a soapstone bird that was looted from Great Zimbabwe
كانت طائر "الحجر الأملس" الذي نهب من زيمبابوي العظمى
in the late 1800s,
في أواخر 1800م،
and is still currently housed in Cecil John Rhodes's estate
ولا يزال يقيم حاليا في ملكية سيسيل جون رودس
in Cape Town.
في كيب تاون.
On that day,
في ذلك اليوم،
I embodied her existence using my body,
لقد جسدت وجودها بإستخدام جسدي،
while standing in the blazing sun for nearly four hours.
بينما أقف في الشمس الحارقة لمدة أربع ساعات تقريبا.
As the time came,
وحين حان الوقت
the crane came alive.
وجاءت الرافعة.
The people did, too --
الشعب، أيضا كان
shouting,
يصرخ،
screaming,
يصيح،
clenching their fists
يرفعون قبضاتهم
and taking pictures of the moment on their phones and cameras.
وبلتقطون الصور لتلك الحظة على هواتفهم وكاميراتهم.
Chapungu's wings,
أجنحة تشابونغو،
along with the crane,
جنبا إلى جنب مع الرافعة،
rose to declare the fall of Cecil John Rhodes.
ارتفعت لتعلن سقوط سيسيل جون رودس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Euphoria filled the air as he became absent from his base,
النشوة ملأت الهواء حين أصبح غائبا عن قاعدته،
while she remained still,
في حين أنها لا تزال قائمة،
very present,
حاضرة جدا
half an hour after his removal.
بعد نصف ساعة من إزالته.
Twenty-three years after apartheid,
وبعد ثلاثة وعشرين عاما من الفصل العنصري،
a new generation of radicals has arisen in South Africa.
جيل جديد من الجذور قد نشأ في جنوب أفريقيا.
The story of Chapungu and Rhodes in the same space and time
قصة تشابونغو ورودس في نفس المكان والزمان
asks important questions
يطرح أسئلة مهمة
related to gender,
المتعلقة بنوع الجنس،
power,
القوة،
self-representation,
تمثيل الذات،
history making
صنع التاريخ
and repatriation.
والعودة إلى الوطن.
From then on,
منذ ذلك الحين،
I realized that my spiritual beliefs and dreams
أدركت أن معتقداتي الروحية وأحلامي
texture my material reality.
تنسج واقعي المادي.
But for me, Chapungu's story felt incomplete.
ولكن بالنسبة لي، شعرت ان قصة تشابونغو ناقصة.
This soapstone bird,
طيرالحجر الأملس هذا
a spiritual medium and messenger of God and the ancestors,
وسيط روحي ورسول من الله والأجداد،
needed me to continue her story.
كان بحاجة لي لمواصلة قصته.
And so I dabbled in the dream space a little bit more,
وهكذا غصت في فضاء الحلم اكثر قليلا،
and this is how "Falling" was born.
وهذه هي الطريقة التي ولدت "السقوط".
[A film by Sethembile Msezane]
[فيلم سيثمبيل مززان]
(Video) (A capella singing)
(فيديو) (غناء كابيلا )
[FALLING]
(السقوط)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In the film,
في الفيلم،
Zimbabwe, South Africa and Germany share a common story
زمبابوي، وجنوب أفريقيا، وألمانيا تتشارك قصة مشتركة
about the soapstone birds that were looted from Great Zimbabwe.
عن طيور الحجرالاملس التي نهبت من زيمبابوي العظمى.
After Zimbabwe gained its independence,
بعد أن حصلت زمبابوي على استقلالها،
all the birds except for one were returned to the monument.
جميع الطيور باستثناء واحد أعيدت إلى النصب التذكاري.
"Falling" explores the mythological belief that there will be unrest
"السقوط" يكشف الاعتقاد الأسطوري بأنه ستكون هناك اضطرابات
until the final bird is returned.
حتى يتم إرجاع الطائر الأخير.
Through my work,
من خلال عملي،
I have realized a lot about the world around me:
لقد أدركت الكثير حول العالم من حولي:
how we move through spaces,
كيف نتحرك عبر المساحات،
who we choose to celebrate
من الذي نختاره للإحتفال
and who we remember.
والذي نتذكره.
Now I look in the mirror and not only see an image of myself,
الآن أنظر في المرآة ولا ارى صورة لنفسي فقط ،
but of the women who have made me who I am today.
ولكن للنساء الذين جعلوني من أنا اليوم.
I stand tall in my work,
أقف طويلة القامة في عملي،
celebrating women's histories,
إحتفالا بتاريخ المرأة،
in the hope that perhaps one day,
على أمل أنه ربما في يوم من الأيام،
no little black girl has to ever feel
لن تشعر فتاة سوداء ابدا.
like she doesn't exist.
كانها غير موجودة.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)